<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="chantey.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE chantey SYSTEM "chantey.dtd">
<chantey>
    <title>Tacking Ship Off Shore</title>
    <collection>1894BMORCOM</collection>
    <author>
        <personid>Trad</personid>
    </author>
    <ID>R023387</ID>

<text>
The weather leech of the topsail shivers,
    The bowlines strain and the lee shrouds slacken;
The braces are taut and the live boom quivers,
    As the waves with the coming squal-cloud blacken.

Open one point on the weather bow,
    Is the light-house tall on Fire Island Head;
There's a shade of doubt on the Captain's brow,
    And the pilot watches the heaving lead.

I stand at the wheel, and with eager eye
    To sea and to sky, and to shore I gaze,
Till the muttered order of "Full and by"
    Is suddenly changed to "Full for stays."

The ship bends lowerbefore the breeze,
    As her broadside fair to the blast she lays,
And shee swifter springs to the rising seas
    As the pilot calls "Stand by for stays!"

It is silence all, as each in his place,
    With the gathered coil in his hardened hands,
By tack and bowline, by sheet and brace,
    Waiting the watchword, impatient stands.

And the light on Fire Island Head draws near,
    As trumpet-winged, the pilot's shout
From his post on the bowsprit's heel I hear,
    With the welcom call of "Ready, about!"

No time to spare: 'tis touch and go,
    And the Captain growls, "Down helm! Hard Down!"
As my weight on the whirling spokes I throw,
While heaven grows black with the storm-clouds frown.

High o'er the knight-heads flies the spray,
    As we meet the shock of the plunging sea,
And my shoulder stiff to the wheel I lay,
    As I answer, "Aye, aye, sir, hard a lee!"

With the swerving leap of a startled steed,
    The ship flies fast in the eye of the wind,
The dangerous shoals on the lee recede,
    And the headland white we have left behind.

The topsails flutter, the jibs collapse,
    And belly and tug at the groaning cleats,
The spanker slaps, and the mainsail flaps,
    And thunders the order, "Tacks and sheets!"

'Mid the rattle of block, and the tramp of the crew,
    Hisses the rain of the rushing squall,
The sails are aback from clew to clew,
    And now is the moment for "Mainsail haul!"

And the heavy yards, like a baby's toy,
    By fifty strong arms are swiftly swung;
She holds her way, and I look with joy,
    For the first white spray o'er the bulwarks flung.

"Let go and haul!" 'tis the last command,
    And the head-sails fill to the blast once more,
Astern and to leeward lies the land,
    With its breakers white on the shingly shore.

What matters the reef or the rain or the squall,
    I steady the helm for the open sea;
The first mat clamors "Belay there all,"
    And the Captain's breath once more comes free.

And so off shore let the good ship fly,
    Little I care how the gusts may blow;
In my fo'castle bunk in a jacket dry,
    Eight bells have struck and my watch is below.
</text>

</chantey>

